Inventory of the Samuel Sloan Walker papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Samuel Sloan Walker papers
1951-1963
Walker, Samuel Sloan
2001C58
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
11 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (4.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter, relating to activities of the Free Europe Committee in promoting opposition to the communist regimes of Eastern Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty corporate records, Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty broadcast records, Hoover Institution Archives
George Caputineanu Minden papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Arch Puddington collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Leszek Gawlikowski interviews, Hoover Institution Archives
Albert H. Arkus papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Free Europe Press issuances, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Samuel Sloan Walker was vice president of the Free Europe Committee (FEC) from 1950 to 1959, where he was responsible for printed word programs. As New York-based director of the Free Europe Press, a division of the FEC parallel to Radio Free Europe, he oversaw publication projects intended for the Western reader, such as the magazine News From Behind the Iron Curtain (later titled East Europe) and its foreign language counterparts. He also oversaw printed word projects intended for audiences in the East, such as leaflets delivered by balloon and mail. After 1956, he launched a book program in which travelers would mail and deliver Western books, mostly non-political, to Eastern Europe. He oversaw the program in an FEC-spin-off, the East European Institute (EEI), based in New York in 1958-1959. Later in his career, Walker devoted himself to publishing, establishing Walker Publishers in New York City.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Samuel S. Walker papers contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter related to activities of the Free Europe Committee in promoting opposition to the communist regimes of Eastern Europe. The collection includes publications produced or sponsored by the Free Europe Committee (FEC) and East Europe Institute (EEI), materials related to a project to distribute Western books at the Vienna Youth Festival of 1959, and corporate records of the EEI.
Walker coordinated a program to distribute books at the Communist-sponsored Vienna Youth Festival of 1959. The program aimed to counterbalance the pro-Communist effects of the Vienna Youth Festival by contributing 155,000 publications (including copies of Dr. Zhivago) to distribute before, during, and after the festival. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports detailing this program.
The collection documents Walker's role in the East Europe Institute (EEI) and includes material documenting the life cycle of the organization, such as the articles of incorporation, by-laws, meeting minutes, and papers of dissolution.
Free Europe Committee.; Anti-communist movements.; Europe, Eastern.
- Vienna Youth Festival correspondence and memoranda, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence with Robert H. Bass, Mucio Delagdo, C. D. Jackson, Fritz P. Molden, and George A. Trutnovsky
- Istanbul trip, 1953 (Box 1)
- "Hungary Since the Twentieth Party Congress," Free Europe Press Plans and Analysis Department, 1956 (Box 1)
- Printed matter, 1956-1959, undated (Box 1)
- Berlin meeting notes, 1955 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  - Bowles, Chester, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Jackson, C. D., 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - Vienna Youth Festival, 1959 (Box 2)
- Free Europe Committee memoranda, 1955 (Box 2)
- Free Europe Press project reports and correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  Includes report on producing leaflets for political warfare purposes
- Free Youth Action project, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
- Photographs of book storage, undated (Box 2)
- Radio Free Europe Poland scripts, 1956 (Box 2)
- Speeches, 1956, undated (Box 2)
  Includes draft of speech for General Crittenberger, Crusade Dinner
- Translations, including Polonia Book Fund, undated (Box 2)
  General note
  On photographic paper. See also box 3
- Travel file (Munich and European trip), 1955-1965 (Box 2)
- Printed matter
  - Publications about Kadar and Hungary, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - Behind the Iron Curtain, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
- Publications Development Corporation proposal, undated (Box 3)
  On photographic paper
- Vienna Youth Festival correspondence, memoranda, reports, and book program outline, 1958-1959 (Box 4)
- Printed matter, 1952-1960 (Box 4)
- East Europe Institute (EEI) project descriptions, undated (Box 4)
  Discusses literature distribution in Poland without attribution to the Free Europe Committee (FEC)
- Map comparing Imperial and Soviet Russian expansion in Europe, Assembly of Captive Europe Nations, 1958 (Box 5)
- Printed matter, 1951-1963 (Box 5-7)
  Includes publications of Free Europe Press (FEP) and Free Europe Committee (FEC)
- East Europe Institute (EEI) corporate records, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
  Includes articles of incorporation, by-laws, and meeting minutes
- Vienna Youth Festival correspondence, memoranda, and action plan, 1958-1959 (Box 8)
- East Europe Institute (EEI) correspondence, memoranda, and budget plan, 1957-1959 (Box 8)
- Printed matter, 1953-1957 (Box 9)
- East Europe Institute (EEI) correspondence, monthly reports, and catalogs, 1959 (Box 9)
  Includes letters of John G. Kirk, Margaret Evans, Unity Evans, and Andrzej Stypulkowski and correspondence with Roy Publishers. Includes documents related to Person-To-Person Program and Vienna Youth Festival
- East Europe Institute (EEI) correspondence, financial documents, dissolution papers, and Walker's departure letters, 1959-1960 (Box 10)
- Vienna Youth Festival correspondence, reports, notes, Newport Jazz Festival proposal, and Newspaper Project memorandum, 1959 (Box 10)
  Includes letters to or from Francis Bregha and Robert Minton
- Oversize material
  - Poster, undated (Box 11)
  - Wiener Nachrichten, bound newspaper, 1959 (Box 11)
- "Chronology of Events in Hungary," Free Europe Press, early version, 1956 (Box 12)
- International Organizations, serial issues, 1959-1960 (Box 12)